<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<metadata>
  <idinfo>
    <citation>
      <citeinfo>
        <origin>Matt, Serena</origin>
        <origin>Shanley, J.B.</origin>
        <origin>Chalmers, A.T.</origin>
        <origin>Sebestyen, S.D. </origin>
        <origin>Merriam, J.L. </origin>
        <origin>Bailey, S.W.</origin>
        <origin>Campbell, J.L.</origin>
        <origin>Ryan, K.A.</origin>
        <origin>Denner, J.C.</origin>
        <origin>Clark, S.F. </origin>
        <origin>Schuster, P.F. </origin>
        <origin>Smith, T.E.</origin>
        <pubdate>20210416</pubdate>
        <title>Sleepers River Laboratory Information</title>
        <geoform>tabular digital data</geoform>
        <othercit>This metadata file describes 1 of the 6 data tables published together (see Larger Work section).</othercit>
        <onlink>https://doi.org/10.5066/P9380HQG</onlink>
        <lworkcit>
          <citeinfo>
            <origin>Matt, Serena</origin>
            <origin>Shanley, J.B.</origin>
            <origin>Chalmers, A.T.</origin>
            <origin>Sebestyen, S.D. </origin>
            <origin>Merriam, J.L. </origin>
            <origin>Bailey, S.W.</origin>
            <origin>Campbell, J.L.</origin>
            <origin>Ryan, K.A.</origin>
            <origin>Denner, J.C.</origin>
            <origin>Clark, S.F. </origin>
            <origin>Schuster, P.F. </origin>
            <origin>Smith, T.E.</origin>
            <pubdate>20210416</pubdate>
            <title>Aqueous chemistry database, Sleepers River Research Watershed, Danville, Vermont, 1991-2018</title>
            <geoform>tabular digital data</geoform>
            <onlink>https://doi.org/10.5066/P9380HQG</onlink>
          </citeinfo>
        </lworkcit>
      </citeinfo>
    </citation>
    <descript>
      <abstract>	Eighteen different laboratories contributed to the chemistry and isotope database of the Sleepers River project during its nearly 30-year duration. This file serves as a central repository for the quality metrics on these data, including accuracy, precision, and limits of detection.  Various methods were used to assimilate the data including direct communication with the laboratories, published papers and reports, and substituting industry standards where the information was unavailable. Each unique combination of laboratory, analyte, and analytical method has its own line in the table, often with annotated comments that elaborate on sources and/or give references.</abstract>
      <purpose>It was efficient to present this information in a compact way in a dedicated file, thereby avoiding several columns of repetitive information in the main chemistry file. </purpose>
    </descript>
    <timeperd>
      <timeinfo>
        <rngdates>
          <begdate>19910801</begdate>
          <enddate>20181231</enddate>
        </rngdates>
      </timeinfo>
      <current>publication date</current>
    </timeperd>
    <status>
      <progress>Complete</progress>
      <update>Annually</update>
    </status>
    <spdom>
      <bounding>
        <westbc>-72.1877</westbc>
        <eastbc>-72.0346</eastbc>
        <northbc>44.5322</northbc>
        <southbc>44.4289</southbc>
      </bounding>
    </spdom>
    <keywords>
      <theme>
        <themekt>ISO 19115 Topic Category</themekt>
        <themekey>location</themekey>
      </theme>
      <theme>
        <themekt>None</themekt>
        <themekey>Sleepers River</themekey>
        <themekey>stream chemistry</themekey>
        <themekey>climate change</themekey>
        <themekey>precipitation</themekey>
        <themekey>groundwater</themekey>
        <themekey>soil water</themekey>
        <themekey>snowmelt</themekey>
        <themekey>W-9</themekey>
        <themekey>concentration-discharge</themekey>
        <themekey>accuracy</themekey>
        <themekey>precision</themekey>
        <themekey>detection limit</themekey>
        <themekey>headwater</themekey>
      </theme>
      <place>
        <placekt>None</placekt>
        <placekey>Danville</placekey>
        <placekey>Sleepers River</placekey>
        <placekey>Connecticut River basin</placekey>
        <placekey>Vermont</placekey>
      </place>
    </keywords>
    <accconst>None.  Please see 'Distribution Info' for details.</accconst>
    <useconst>None.  Users are advised to read the dataset's metadata thoroughly to understand appropriate use and data limitations.</useconst>
    <ptcontac>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntper>Serena Matt</cntper>
          <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey, NORTHEAST REGION</cntorg>
        </cntperp>
        <cntpos>Physical Scientist</cntpos>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing address</addrtype>
          <address>PO Box 628</address>
          <city>Montpelier</city>
          <state>VT</state>
          <postal>05601</postal>
          <country>US</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>802-828-4512</cntvoice>
        <cntfax>802-828-4465</cntfax>
        <cntemail>smatt@usgs.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </ptcontac>
    <datacred>U.S. Geological Survey Land Change Science</datacred>
  </idinfo>
  <dataqual>
    <attracc>
      <attraccr>This table presents analytical method accuracy and precision for every unique combination of laboratory and analyte reported in "1. Sleepers River Aqueous Chemistry.csv."  Accuracy and precision values were assembled using laboratory communications and published methods. When we could not obtain values directly from the laboratory we estimated them using industry standards. Estimated values have been flagged accordingly. See "Process Steps" and "Overview Description" for a detailed description of calculations and data table organization.</attraccr>
    </attracc>
    <logic>Data have been thoroughly checked.</logic>
    <complete>Dataset is considered complete for the information presented 08/01/1991-12/31/2018.</complete>
    <lineage>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>	This comma delimited (CSV) table, "3. Sleepers River Laboratory Information Metadata," summarizes the detection limit (DL), analytical method, method quality-assurance (QA or accuracy), and method quality-control (QC or precision) for every unique combination of laboratory and chemical or isotopic constituent reported in “1. Sleepers River Aqueous Chemistry.csv.”
	Detection limits were either already embedded in the data originally received from a laboratory or were provided via written communication with the laboratory. In a small number of cases, the detection limit was either unavailable or embedded in the data non-numerically (such as with a "&lt;" symbol). In these cases, detection limits were inferred from the data or from other laboratories using the same method.  Median DLs are reported when DLs varied by analytical run or dilution. Because ranges were sometimes wide, the median was thought to better reflect the central tendency of the detection limit. Special circumstances, such as when median DLs are reported rather than single values, DLs are unknown and inferred from other laboratories, or when DLs were originally embedded in the data non-numerically, are noted in the "DL_Comments" column. Note that if a chemical concentration is less than its DL it is reported in “1. Sleepers River Aqueous Chemistry.csv” as the negative DL except for ANC.µeq.L, d13C, d2H, d18O, d15N.NO3, d18O.NO3, 87Sr.86Sr, and Temp.C,which can be measured as negative values and do not have corresponding DLs in this table.
	Methods were also obtained via written communication with individual laboratories. If the laboratory method used to analyze a given chemical analyte is published, it is referenced in the "Methods_Reference" column and full citations can be found in the "Citations" field under the "Overview Description" section of this metadata file. 
	 Accuracy and precision values were obtained either from written communication with individual laboratories or from the laboratory’s published methods. All accuracy  values are presented using the metric of either median or mean percent error (PE),depending on the lab, where PE=( |Measured-Actual| / Actual) × 100 unless otherwise noted. For example, some accuracies were originally expressed as plus or minus (±)  concentration and they are presented as such in this table. "Measured" and "Actual" refer to the measured or actual QC sample concentration.  All precision values are presented using the metric of the coefficient of variation (CV) where CV is calculated for multiple QC samples of a given reference concentration and expressed on a percent basis as CV = (Standard Deviation / Mean) × 100 unless otherwise noted. For example, isotope precision is presented as permil ( ‰).  More details about these metrics, such as how they were originally reported by individual laboratories, can be found in the "Accuracy_Precision_Comments" column. 
	If accuracy or precision was unavailable for a given laboratory, analyte, and method, then the most conservative value reported by the other laboratories for that analyte and method was used. If there was no other value for that given analyte and method, then the most conservative value reported in published methods from either the U.S. Geologic Survey (USGS), the Environmental Protection Agency (EPA-NERL), or the American Public Health Association (APHA) Standard Methods was used, depending on the source from which a laboratory would most likely have derived its methods. The inferred value was then additionally cross-checked using the National Environmental Methods Index (NEMI). How a given accuracy or precision value was obtained, whether by written communication, published methods, or inference, is described in the "Accuracy_Precision_Comments" column. Any published reference materials used for obtaining these values are also cited in this column. Full citations can again be found in the "Citations" field under the "Overview Description" section of this metadata file. 
	 Additional metrics of chemical analysis performance can be found in "4. Sleepers River Interlaboratory Comparison.csv," "5. Sleepers River Replicate Statistics.csv," and "6. Sleepers River Blank Statistics.csv."
</procdesc>
        <procdate>20210304</procdate>
      </procstep>
    </lineage>
  </dataqual>
  <eainfo>
    <detailed>
      <enttyp>
        <enttypl>3. Sleepers River Laboratory Information.csv</enttypl>
        <enttypd>This comma delimited (CSV) file contains data on laboratory reporting limits and analytical method QA/QC. NA denotes no data.
NOTE: Software used to open data file may change default column formatting. If opening in Excel, use Data-Import txt to preserve default column formatting.</enttypd>
        <enttypds>Producer Defined</enttypds>
      </enttyp>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Laboratory_Key</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>A number corresponding to a laboratory, identified in the “Laboratory” column, at which a given analyte was analyzed. This number is also reported in “1. Sleepers River Aqueous Chemistry.csv” such that every chemical analyte concentration has a corresponding laboratory source.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Producer Defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>See column definition.</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Laboratory</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>The laboratory at which a given chemical analyte was analyzed. The laboratory can also be identified using the corresponding number from the "Laboratory_Key" column. This number is also reported in “1. Sleepers River Aqueous Chemistry.csv” such that every chemical analyte concentration has a corresponding laboratory source.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Producer Defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>See column definition.</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
  <attrlabl>Analyte</attrlabl><attrdef>The chemical or isotopic constituent analyzed by a given laboratory.  The analyte names reported in this column also appear as column names in “1. Sleepers River Aqueous Chemistry.csv.”</attrdef><attrdefs>Producer Defined</attrdefs><attrdomv>
    <edom>
      <edomv>Al.µg.L</edomv>
      <edomvd>Aluminum measured in micrograms per liter (µg/L)</edomvd>
      <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
    </edom>
  </attrdomv>
  <attrdomv>
    <edom>
      <edomv>Alm.µg.L</edomv>
      <edomvd>Total monomeric aluminum measured in micrograms per liter (µg/L)</edomvd>
      <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
    </edom>
  </attrdomv>
  <attrdomv>
    <edom>
      <edomv>Alo.µg.L</edomv>
      <edomvd>Organic monomeric aluminum measured in micrograms per liter (µg/L)</edomvd>
      <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
    </edom>
  </attrdomv>
  <attrdomv>
    <edom>
      <edomv>ANC.µeq.L</edomv>
      <edomvd>Acid neutralizing capacity measured in microequivalents per liter (µeq/L)</edomvd>
      <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
    </edom>
  </attrdomv>
  <attrdomv>
    <edom>
      <edomv>Ba.µg.L</edomv>
      <edomvd>Barium measured in micrograms per liter (µg/L)</edomvd>
      <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
    </edom>
  </attrdomv>
  <attrdomv>
    <edom>
      <edomv>Ca.µeq.L</edomv>
      <edomvd>Calcium measured in microequivalents per liter (µeq/L)</edomvd>
      <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
    </edom>
  </attrdomv>
  <attrdomv>
    <edom>
      <edomv>Cl.µeq.L</edomv>
      <edomvd>Chloride measured in microequivalents per liter (µeq/L)</edomvd>
      <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
    </edom>
  </attrdomv>
  <attrdomv>
    <edom>
      <edomv>d13C</edomv>
      <edomvd>Carbon 13C/12C isotope mass ratio presented as permil deviation from the Pee Dee Belemnite standard</edomvd>
      <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
    </edom>
  </attrdomv>
  <attrdomv>
    <edom>
      <edomv>d2H</edomv>
      <edomvd>Hydrogen 2H/1H isotope mass ratio in water, presented as permil deviation from Vienna Standard Mean Ocean Water (VSMOW)</edomvd>
      <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
    </edom>
  </attrdomv>
  <attrdomv>
    <edom>
      <edomv>d18O</edomv>
      <edomvd>Oxygen 18O/16O isotope mass ratio in water, presented as permil deviation from Vienna Standard Mean Ocean Water (VSMOW)</edomvd>
      <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
    </edom>
  </attrdomv>
  <attrdomv>
    <edom>
      <edomv>d15N.NO3</edomv>
      <edomvd>Nitrogen 15N/14N isotope mass ratio in nitrate, presented as permil deviation from atmospheric composition</edomvd>
      <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
    </edom>
  </attrdomv>
  <attrdomv>
    <edom>
      <edomv>d18O.NO3</edomv>
      <edomvd>Oxygen18O/16O isotope mass ratio in nitrate, presented as permil deviation from Vienna Standard Mean Ocean Water (VSMOW)</edomvd>
      <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
    </edom>
  </attrdomv>
  <attrdomv>
    <edom>
      <edomv>DOC.mg.L</edomv>
      <edomvd>Dissolved organic carbon measured in milligrams per liter (mg/L)</edomvd>
      <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
    </edom>
  </attrdomv>
  <attrdomv>
    <edom>
      <edomv>Fe.µg.L</edomv>
      <edomvd>Iron measured in micrograms per liter (µg/L)</edomvd>
      <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
    </edom>
  </attrdomv>
  <attrdomv>
    <edom>
      <edomv>K.µeq.L</edomv>
      <edomvd>Potassium measured in microequivalents per liter (µeq/L)</edomvd>
      <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
    </edom>
  </attrdomv>
  <attrdomv>
    <edom>
      <edomv>Li.µg.L</edomv>
      <edomvd>Lithium measured in micrograms per liter (µg/L)</edomvd>
      <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
    </edom>
  </attrdomv>
  <attrdomv>
    <edom>
      <edomv>Mg.µeq.L</edomv>
      <edomvd>Magnesium measured in microequivalents per liter (µeq/L)</edomvd>
      <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
    </edom>
  </attrdomv>
  <attrdomv>
    <edom>
      <edomv>Mn.µg.L</edomv>
      <edomvd>Manganese measured in micrograms per liter (µg/L)</edomvd>
      <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
    </edom>
  </attrdomv>
  <attrdomv>
    <edom>
      <edomv>Na.µeq.L</edomv>
      <edomvd>Sodium measured in microequivalents per liter (µeq/L)</edomvd>
      <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
    </edom>
  </attrdomv>
  <attrdomv>
    <edom>
      <edomv>NH4.µeq.L</edomv>
      <edomvd>Ammonium measured in microequivalents per liter (µeq/L)</edomvd>
      <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
    </edom>
  </attrdomv>
  <attrdomv>
    <edom>
      <edomv>NO3.µeq.L</edomv>
      <edomvd>Nitrate measured in microequivalents per liter (µeq/L)</edomvd>
      <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
    </edom>
  </attrdomv>
  <attrdomv>
    <edom>
      <edomv>pH</edomv>
      <edomvd>pH unit</edomvd>
      <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
    </edom>
  </attrdomv>
  <attrdomv>
    <edom>
      <edomv>PO4.mg.P.L</edomv>
      <edomvd>Phosphate measured in milligrams per liter (mg/L)</edomvd>
      <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
    </edom>
  </attrdomv>
  <attrdomv>
    <edom>
      <edomv>Si.µmol.L</edomv>
      <edomvd>Silicon measured in micromoles per liter (µmol/L)</edomvd>
      <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
    </edom>
  </attrdomv>
  <attrdomv>
    <edom>
      <edomv>SO4.µeq.L</edomv>
      <edomvd>Sulfate measured in microequivalents per liter (µeq/L)</edomvd>
      <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
    </edom>
  </attrdomv>
  <attrdomv>
    <edom>
      <edomv>SpCond.µS.cm</edomv>
      <edomvd>Specific conductivity measured in microsiemens per centimeter (µS/cm)</edomvd>
      <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
    </edom>
  </attrdomv>
  <attrdomv>
    <edom>
      <edomv>87Sr.86Sr</edomv>
      <edomvd>Strontium 87Sr/86Sr isotope mass ratio.</edomvd>
      <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
    </edom>
  </attrdomv>
  <attrdomv>
    <edom>
      <edomv>Sr.µg.L</edomv>
      <edomvd>Strontium measured in micrograms per liter (µg/L)</edomvd>
      <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
    </edom>
  </attrdomv>
  <attrdomv>
    <edom>
      <edomv>TDN.mg.L</edomv>
      <edomvd>Total dissolved nitrogen measured in milligrams per liter (mg/L)</edomvd>
      <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
    </edom>
  </attrdomv>
  <attrdomv>
    <edom>
      <edomv>TDP.mg.L</edomv>
      <edomvd>Total dissolved phosphorus measured in milligrams per liter (mg/L)</edomvd>
      <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
    </edom>
  </attrdomv>
  <attrdomv>
    <edom>
      <edomv>Temp.C</edomv>
      <edomvd>Temperature measured in degrees celsius (C)</edomvd>
      <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
    </edom>
  </attrdomv>
  <attrdomv>
    <edom>
      <edomv>UV254.cm.1</edomv>
      <edomvd>Ultraviolet (UV)-absorbance at 254 nanometers reported in cm-1</edomvd>
      <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
    </edom>
  </attrdomv>
</attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Analytical_Method</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>The laboratory method used to analyze a given chemical analyte.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Producer Defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv><udom>See column definition.</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Method_Reference</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>If the laboratory method reported in the "Analytical_Method" column is published, it is referenced here. Complete citations can be found in the "Supplemental Information" section of this metadata file.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Producer Defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv><udom>See column definition.</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>DL</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Detection limits (DLs) are summarized for each laboratory, chemical analyte, and analytical method combination.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Producer Defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
  <edomv>NA</edomv>
  <edomvd>No Data</edomvd>
  <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
</edom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv><rdom>
            <rdommin>0.003</rdommin>
            <rdommax>50.0</rdommax>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>DL_Comments</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Comments for DLs reported in column "DL"  such as when median DLs are reported as opposed to single vales, DLs are unknown and inferred from other laboratories, or when DLs were originally embedded in the data non-numerically. For example, "&lt;DL" was reported instead of an actual value. See comments for details.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Producer Defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
  <edomv>NA</edomv>
  <edomvd>No Data</edomvd>
  <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
</edom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv><udom>See column definition.</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Accuracy</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Accuracy of a given laboratory, method, and analyte combination presented as percent error (PE) where PE=(|Measured Value of QC sample-Actual Value of QC sample| / Actual Value of QC Sample)×100, unless otherwise noted. Either a median or mean PE is reported depending on the laboratory, which is further specified in the "Accuracy_Precision_Comments" column.  Unit of measure is percent unless otherwise noted. </attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Producer Defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>See column definition.</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Precision</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Precision of a given laboratory, method, and analyte combination presented as the coefficient of variation (CV) where CV=(Standard Deviation/Mean)×100, unless otherwise noted. CV is calculated for multiple QC samples of a given reference concentration.  Unit of measure is percent unless otherwise noted.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Producer Defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>See column definition.</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Accuracy_Precision_Comments</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Describes how the accuracy and precision values were obtained, whether by written communication, published methods, or inference, and cites references used. Describes if the values were reported differently in their original source. Complete citations can be found in the "Supplemental Information" section of this metadata file.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Producer Defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv><udom>See column definition.</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Count</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Count reports the number of records in “1. Sleepers River Aqueous Chemistry.csv” for each given laboratory, analyte, and method combination.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Producer Defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv><rdom>
            <rdommin>1</rdommin>
            <rdommax>4565</rdommax>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Years_Collected</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Sample collection date range, as month and year, for a given laboratory, analyte, and method combination.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Producer Defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv><udom>See column definition.</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Years_Comments</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Describes unusual distribution of samples collected during the Years_Collected date range such as a long gap.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Producer Defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv><udom>See column definition.</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
    </detailed>
    <overview>
      <eaover>	This file contains information about the laboratories and analytical methods used to analyze chemistry presented in “1. Sleepers River Aqueous Chemistry.csv.”  All combinations of laboratory, chemical analyte, and analytical method are reported by row and sorted by analyte, start date of sample collection, and end date of sample collection; except that the most recently used laboratory always appears last for a given analyte.  Note that there can be more than one record for each analyte/laboratory combination when methods change as indicated by different applicable date ranges in the “Years_Collected” column.  If a given analyte was continuously  measured by a laboratory but appears in two rows due to a method change, then those rows are kept consecutive regardless of the sorting logic.  </eaover>
      <eadetcit>Bullen, T.D., Krabbenhoft, D.P., and Kendall, C.,1996, Kinetic and mineralogic controls on the evolution of groundwater chemistry and 87Sr/86Sr in a sandy silicate aquifer, northern Wisconsin, USA: Geochimica et Cosmochimica Acta 60(10), pp.1807-1821.

Doctor, D. H., Kendall, C., Sebestyen, S. D., Shanley, J. B., Ohte, N., and Boyer, E. W, 2008, Carbon isotope fractionation of dissolved inorganic carbon (DIC) due to outgassing of carbon dioxide from a headwater stream: Hydrological Processes: An International Journal 22(14), pp.2410-2423.

Fishman, M.J., and Friedman,L.C.,1989, Methods for determination of inorganic substances in water and fluvial sediments: U.S. Geological Survey Techniques of Water-Resources Investigations, book 5, chap. A1.

Garbarino, J.R., Kanagy, L.K., and Cree, M.E., 2006, Determination of elements in natural-water, biota, sediment, and soil samples using collision/reaction cell inductively coupled plasma–mass spectrometry:  U.S. Geological Survey Techniques and Methods, book 5, sec. B, chap. 1.

Kaur, A.J., Ross, D.S., Shanley, J.B. and Yatzor, A.R., 2016, Enriched groundwater seeps in two Vermont headwater catchments are hotspots of nitrate turnover: Wetlands, 36(2), pp.237-249.

Kendall, Kimberly A., J. B. Shanley, and McDonnell,J.J., 1999, A hydrometric and geochemical approach to test the transmissivity feedback hypothesis during snowmelt: Journal of Hydrology 219.3(4), pp. 188-205.

Lawrence, G.B., Lincoln, T.A., Horan-Ross, D.A., Olson, M.L., and Waldron, L.A., 1995, Analytical methods of the U.S. Geological Survey's New York District Water-Analysis Laboratory: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 1995–0416, 78 p., https://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/ofr95416.

Lincoln, T. A., Horan-Ross, D.A., McHale, M.R., and Lawrence, G.B., 1996, Quality-assurance data for routine water analyses by the US Geological Survey Laboratory in Troy, New York, July 1991 through June 1993:  U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 96-167.

Lincoln, T. A., Horan-Ross, D.A., McHale, M.R., and Lawrence, G.B., 2001, Quality-assurance data for routine water analyses by the US Geological Survey Laboratory in Troy, New York, July 1993 through June 1995:  U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 2001-71.

Lincoln, T. A., Horan-Ross, D.A., McHale, M.R., and Lawrence, G.B., 2001, Quality-assurance data for routine water analyses by the US Geological Survey Laboratory in Troy, New York, July 1993 through June 1995:  U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 2001-71.

Lincoln, T. A., Horan-Ross, D.A., McHale, M.R., and Lawrence, G.B., 2005, Quality-assurance data for routine water analyses by the US Geological Survey Laboratory in Troy, New York, July 1995 through June 1997:  U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 2004-1327.

Lincoln, T. A., Horan-Ross, D.A., McHale, M.R., and Lawrence, G.B., 2006, Quality-assurance data for routine water analyses by the US Geological Survey Laboratory in Troy, New York, July 1999 through June 2001:  U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 2006-1246.

Merriam, J., McDowell, W. H., and Currie, W. S., 1996, A High-Temperature Catalytic Oxidation Technique for Determining Total Dissolved Nitrogen: Soil Science Society of America Journal 60(4), pp.1050-1055

Potter, B. B., and Wimsatt, J., 2009, Method 415.3 (Rev. 1.2): Determination of Total Organic Carbon and Specific UV Absorbance at 254 nm in Source Water and Drinking Water: U.S. Environmental Protection Agency.

Rounds, S.A., 2012, Alkalinity and acid neutralizing capacity (ver. 4.0, September 2012): U.S. Geological Survey Techniques of Water-Resources Investigations, book 9, chap. 6.6, https://doi.org/10.3133/twri09A6.6.

Sebestyen, S.D., Boyer, E.W., Shanley, J.B., Kendall, C., Doctor, D.H., Aiken, G.R. and Ohte, N., 2008, Sources, transformations, and hydrological processes that control stream nitrate and dissolved organic matter concentrations during snowmelt in an upland forest: Water Resources Research, 44(12).

Sebestyen, S.D., Kendall, C., Elliott, E.M., Schiff, S.L., Barnes, R.T., Bostic, J.T., Buda, A.R., Burns, D.A., Campbell, J.L., Dail, D.B. and Eshleman, K.N., Keith, N., Fernandez, I.J., Finlay, J.C., Goodale, C.L., Griffiths, N.A., Hall, S.J., Lawrence, G.B., Lovett, G.M., McHale, P.J., Mitchell, M.J., Nelson, D.M., Nelson, S.J., Ohte, N., Pardo, L.H., Rose, L.A., Ross, D.S., Sabo, R.D., Shanley, J.B., Shattuck, M.D., Spoelstra, J., Weintraub, S.R., Wickman, T.R., and Williard, K.W. J., 2019, Nitrate isotope database for meteoric waters, surface waters, soil waters, and groundwaters. Fort Collins,CO: Forest Service Research Data Archive. https://doi.org/10.2737/RDS-2019-0003

Standard Method 2320B Alkalinity, Standard Methods for the Examination of Water and Wastewater,23rd.https://doi.org/10.2105/SMWW.2882.023

Standard Method 5310B Total Organic Carbon (TOC), Standard Methods for the Examination of Water and Wastewater,23rd. https://doi.org/10.2105/SMWW.2882.104

Standard Method 5310D Total Organic Carbon (TOC), Standard Methods for the Examination of Water and Wastewater,23rd. https://doi.org/10.2105/SMWW.2882.104

Standard Method 5910B UV-Absorbing Organic Constituents, Standard Methods for the Examination of Water and Wastewater,23rd. https://doi.org/10.2105/SMWW.2882.113

Wlide, F.D., 2008, Field Measurements: U.S. Geological Survey Techniques of Water-Resources Investigations, book 9, chap. A6, https://doi.org/10.3133/twri09A6.

U.S. Environmental Protection Agency, 1994, Method 200.7: Determination of Metals and Trace Elements in Water and Wastes by Inductively Coupled Plasma-Atomic Emission Spectrometry, Revision 4.4. Cincinnati, OH.

U.S. Environmental Protection Agency, 1997, Method 300.1: Determination of Inorganic Anions in Drinking Water by Ion Chromatography, Revision 1.0. Cincinnati, OH.

U.S. Environmental Protection Agency, 1979, Methods for the Chemical Analysis of Water and Wastes, EPA-600/4–79-020.</eadetcit>
    </overview>
  </eainfo>
  <distinfo>
    <distrib>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntper>GS ScienceBase</cntper>
          <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey</cntorg>
        </cntperp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing address</addrtype>
          <address>Denver Federal Center, Building 810, Mail Stop 302</address>
          <city>Denver</city>
          <state>CO</state>
          <postal>80225</postal>
          <country>United States</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>1-888-275-8747</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>sciencebase@usgs.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </distrib>
    <distliab>Unless otherwise stated, all data, metadata and related materials are considered to satisfy the quality standards relative to the purpose for which the data were collected. Although these data and associated metadata have been reviewed for accuracy and completeness and approved for release by the U.S. Geological Survey (USGS), no warranty expressed or implied is made regarding the display or utility of the data on any other system or for general or scientific purposes, nor shall the act of distribution constitute any such warranty.  Any use of trade, firm, or product names is for descriptive purposes only and does not imply endorsement by the U.S. Government.</distliab>
    <stdorder>
      <digform><digtinfo>
          <formname>Digital Data</formname>
        </digtinfo>
        <digtopt><onlinopt><computer><networka><networkr>https://doi.org/10.5066/P9380HQG</networkr></networka></computer></onlinopt></digtopt></digform>
      <fees>None</fees>
    </stdorder>
  </distinfo>
  <metainfo>
    <metd>20210304</metd>
    <metc>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntper>Serena Matt</cntper>
          <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey, NORTHEAST REGION</cntorg>
        </cntperp>
        <cntpos>Physical Scientist</cntpos>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing address</addrtype>
          <address>PO Box 628</address>
          <city>Montpelier</city>
          <state>VT</state>
          <postal>05601</postal>
          <country>US</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>802-828-4512</cntvoice>
        <cntfax>802-828-4465</cntfax>
        <cntemail>smatt@usgs.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </metc>
    <metstdn>FGDC Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
    <metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv>
  </metainfo>
</metadata>
